# **ALBERTO BENGOA**

+1 (408) 475-3343

me@albertobengoa.com http://albertobengoa.com/resume A product owner with 10+ years of experience conceptualizing, delivering, and managing high-visibility, high-impact products and projects in cloud and enterprise environments.

Strong computer science background and extensive, up to date coding experience both as an individual contributor and as a technical team manager.

Data expert with deep knowledge of data warehousing, data virtualization, and data integration in enterprise environments, both at the architecture and implementation levels.

Self-driven, adaptable team member with extensive experience in enterprise data privacy compliance, technical partnerships management, technical sales cycles, customer relationship management, and customer training.

# **Work Experience**

# Apple, Inc. - Application Lead, Global Business Intelligence [June 2020 - Present]

- End-to-end owner of Apple's internal EDW product for compliance with consumer privacy laws (GDPR/CCPA):
  - Mission critical engine for Apple's daily worldwide operations, serving tens of billions of daily requests.
  - Enabling secure, compliant ETL processes across more than a dozen systems within EDW and data lake, with tens
    of thousands of daily users (both batch and interactive).
  - Highly scalable, hybrid on-premise/private cloud/public cloud deployment, with no unplanned downtime.

#### • Product management:

- Creating and maintaining the product roadmap and functional requirements: incorporating complex external (Legal, Privacy, Business) and internal requirements (feature enhancements, technical debt reduction, developer productivity improvements).
- Establishing bidirectional communication with all Apple business units to ensure close coordination regarding product releases, production incidents, and new requirement gathering.
- Supporting internal and external audits, demonstrating that the designs and deployed solutions meet the legal and business requirements, while maintaining the company-wide standards for security and privacy.
- Creating and maintaining processes and documentation to ensure smooth onboarding of new resources and new consumers, maintaining high standards of quality during the entire software lifecycle.
- Review architecture and designs, provide technical input to the implementation team, and provide solutions signoff.

#### • Team and business management:

- Prioritizing of work for a team of 16 people worldwide, setting expectations for deadlines and deliverables, and providing oversight for the successful launch of product features.
- Team building: business and technical mentoring of direct and indirect reports, keeping the team members engaged with the product and mission, providing a satisfying and productive work environment during the challenges of remote work.
- Quarterly/yearly planning: defining and tracking multiple parallel project plans, determining necessary resourcing and funding levels for successful execution.
- Creating and maintaining reports of goals, key metrics, product/business milestones, and financial status and projections. Communicating to management the business and financial impact of the application, securing funding for subsequent cycles while reducing capital and operational costs.
- Managing contracting vendors providing workforce for the team. Setting expected levels of delivery quality and conducting periodic reviews with each vendor to ensure the expectations were met or exceeded.

### Datometry, Inc. - Lead Software Architect [November 2018 - June 2020]

- Migrating on-premise Teradata systems to cloud data warehouses (Microsoft Azure SQL Data Warehouse, Amazon Redshift, Google Big Query), using Datometry's proprietary technology.
- Customer facing:
  - In charge of the entire customer-facing pipeline for selected accounts, from first demo to production cutover, including but not limited to: explaining the solution to prospects, creating tailored implementation architectures, project management, solving any technical issues, presenting plans of action and results to key stakeholders, and ensuring any roadblock to full implementation was identified and resolved before becoming an issue.
  - Closed customer accounts #2 and #3 for production, first yearly renewal of customer account #1.
  - Instrumental on closing a 7-figure partner technology deal.
  - Managed cloud partners (Amazon, Microsoft, Google) at the technical and project level, and SI partners for specific implementations (Cognizant, Capgemini, HCL, DxC, etc.).
- Datometry awards: Outstanding contributor, MVP
- Tooling:
  - Personally built the first cross-vendor table synchronization tool in the market, from concept to final product, a
    key enabling technology that allows customers to successfully migrate their data warehouse tables from onpremise to the cloud.
  - Analyzed, designed and presented to customers new tools enabling the co-existence of Datometry's internallydeveloped tooling with Teradata's native tooling in the same system, allowing to execute them side by side.
  - Created tooling for analyzing Datometry's logs, increasing efficiency of all debugging and operational activities.

#### Internal:

- Improved and standardized internal processes for customer-facing activities, achieving traceability of deliverables and status, reusability of assets, and reduction of incremental effort needed for executing new accounts.
- Collaborated with the Engineering and Product teams to ensure functional gaps affecting customer accounts were identified and addressed in a timely fashion, and to provide inputs for mid- and long-term planning for the product roadmap.

## Software Consulting [June 2017 – November 2018]

- Providing end-to-end technical consulting focused on requirement gathering, solution design, implementation, and strategy for both early-stage and established organizations. Projects in the aerospace, higher education, and social good domains include:
  - Architected a centralized cloud platform for managing higher ed curriculum data and student academic progress, implemented first stage for concept validation, and advised the university on expansion of platform into other areas.
  - Designed and implemented <u>DSSG Solve</u>: a self-service web platform for managing volunteer work for Data Science projects in social good domains. The tool intelligently connects volunteers to active projects based on interests and skill sets, lowering the barrier of entry for volunteering, and improving project completion and success rates.
  - Technology and business advisor for a STEM educational institution in the aerospace domain. Advising on customer growth strategy, market penetration, and development of their in-house customer-facing platform.

### Koolock, Inc. - Director of Product [June 2016 - June 2017]

- Koolock is a stealth-mode startup revolutionizing the infrared satellite imagery market. It develops proprietary space
  satellite hardware in order to capture from orbit significantly higher quality data than currently available, and a
  sophisticated software suite to gather data insights for addressing global issues such as deforestation, fishing
  regulatory compliance, and natural disaster detection/prevention.
  - **Product Management.** Identified the product-market fit and the business niche that provided the best match for the novel proprietary technology (the intersection of hardware sensors and the efficient acquisition, processing, analysis and distribution of data to end customers); steered the product and created a roadmap for the innovative platform.
  - **Technical work.** Architected Koolock's platform, created the first satellite imaging processing pipeline (that transforms raw satellite sensor data into a customer-focused catalog of images and highlighted patterns, insights and analytics of the imaging data), and coded the technical demo of the intelligence capabilities enabled by the novel imaging and analytical technologies.

### Denodo Technologies, Inc. - Senior Product Manager [2014 - 2017]

- Product Management.
  - Data virtualization products. Responsible for three of Denodo's data virtualization products, managing them
    during their conceptualization, design, implementation and operation: <u>Denodo Community</u>, <u>Denodo Express</u>, and
    <u>Denodo Platform for AWS</u>.
  - Enterprise ecosystem products. Conceptualized, architected, designed, and prototyped projects that fill gaps in
    the core data virtualization platform: Denodo Testing Tool, <u>Denodo Diagnostics and Monitoring tool</u>, <u>Denodo Solution Manager</u> and Denodo Model Bridge Tool.
- **Technical Partnerships.** Responsible for technical interaction with partners, including the <u>Denodo+IBM partnership</u>, the <u>Tableau-Denodo certification</u>, (which included coding the first prototype of the integration software), the Hadoop certifications (both <u>Cloudera</u> and <u>Hortonworks</u>), and the <u>Snowflake certification</u>.
- Professional Services. Took on architectural engagements, doing work with customers to help them use data
  virtualization, review already started projects to steer them towards success, and apply corrective measures to projects
  in danger of failure.
- Customer Outreach Program. Defined and executed the Denodo Strategic Customer Center initiative, with the goals of
  maintaining the user community up to date about the product's roadmap and gathering feedback about new and
  planned features.
- Technical Writing. Authored two in-depth technical cookbook manuals (<u>Data Warehouse Off-loading</u> and <u>Query Optimization</u>) that contain detailed instructions for both architects and developers on how to solve customer's questions about real-world deployments, increasing awareness and brand value for Denodo.
- Prospective Customer Training. Designed and taught both low-level technical classes and architecture-level courses, including <u>Denodo's monthly data virtualization architect course</u>. Over 150 architects were trained in 2015, and over 250 in 2016.

## Denodo Technologies, Inc. - Professional Services Manager [2010 - 2014]

- Managed all the aspects of post-sale customer relationship and retention, as the main point of contact for the
  customer, being their internal champion and making sure every existing customer became an evangelist for Denodo's
  technology in later sales cycles with other prospective customers.
- Managed the US software engineering team to analyze, design and implement customer projects.
- Worked closely with the CEO and with the Sales VP for North America in reviewing commercial proposals to verify the licensing and professional services terms were realistic, achievable and appropriately priced and presented to customers.

## Denodo Technologies, Inc. - Customer Support / Customer Training Manager [2009 - 2011]

- Managed the customer support team to provide assistance in designing, developing and troubleshooting data virtualization solutions, helping strategic customers to go into production within the planned schedules.
- Helped retain customers through timely resolution of all technical problems, analysis and delivery of new features.
- Managed the training team to teach customers the use of the Denodo Platform, making it possible for them to start using the purchased software right away.
- Participated in the creation of the <u>training curriculum</u> and maintained it through several versions of the Denodo Platform; this set of training courses is taught to virtually all of Denodo's new customers.

## Denodo Technologies, Inc. - Lead User Experience Engineer [2007 - 2009]

- Responsible for continuous analysis of software capabilities, gathering new customer requirements and creation of successful UI designs for the whole suite of the company's enterprise software, of high functional complexity.
- Introduced changes that improved both customer win rate and customer satisfaction, taking into account customer needs, technical feasibility and planning, visual design and user interaction.
- Conceptualized, designed and implemented the Denodo Platform Control Center, a new tool for managing the local installation of the Denodo Platform; in production since then and used by every customer of Denodo.

## Denodo Technologies, Inc. - Software Engineer [2005 - 2007]

- In charge of creating from scratch (first commit) the Denodo Platform client tools: the main Administration/ Development Tool for the data virtualization server, and the Web Automation Design Tool for the web integration server. Both tools are highly interactive, with an extremely deep feature set, and they are used by every customer to develop data virtualization solutions.
- Gained a very strong experience in both desktop and server side development.

# **Education**

### M.S. in Computer Science, summa cum laude [1999 - 2005]

• **University of A Coruña (Spain).** Dissertation (2005): "Decision support system for investment in telecommunication and mobile telephony networks under demand uncertainty". PDF Link (Spanish).

# **Personal Projects & Skills**

- Spoken Languages: Fluent in English, Spanish and Galician. Beginner in Bulgarian.
- <u>TTT</u>: an online, browser-based clone of the classic game <u>Blockout</u> (a 3D Tetris). Built as a fun way of learning new technologies: ClojureScript and <u>reagent</u> + <u>re-frame</u> (ClojureScript bindings for <u>Facebook's React</u>).
- Extensive experience with Clojure, Clojurescript, Java, RDMBS (Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, SQLite...), Web Services, Hadoop (Cloudera, Hortonworks), Data Warehouses (with emphasis on Teradata, Azure SQL Data Warehouse, and Amazon Redshift), cloud technologies, distributed systems, Kafka, NoSQL (Cassandra, Redis), HTML, JavaScript, CSS, etc.
- **Photography**: avid photographer for more than twenty years, shooting with a variety of equipment ranging from digital compacts to large format film cameras, focused mainly in landscapes and portraits.